<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Translation on Will Merrill</title>
    <link>http://lambdaviking.com/categories/translation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Translation on Will Merrill</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="http://lambdaviking.com/categories/translation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wanderer</title>
      <link>http://lambdaviking.com/post/the-wanderer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lambdaviking.com/post/the-wanderer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Often the outcast
awaits his grace,
the Lord&amp;rsquo;s mercy,
though he, sorrow-minded,
must turn his oars
along the waters,
wade the path of exile.
Fate goes always as it must!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So spoke the earth-stepper,
mindful of his misfortunes,
of wrathful slaughter,
the death of his comrades:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often in the morning,
I had to discuss
my every trouble alone.
There is no one living
that I dare open my innermost thought to.
Truly I know
that it ought to be among men,
the noble custom,
where one secures the chest of his spirit,
hordes his treasure case,
thinks and speaks freely.
The weary spirit cannot
withstand fate,
nor does the bitter mind
help do any good.
So the glory-yearning
often lock away their dreary
thoughts in their breast-coffins.
So I,
often wretched
and besorrowed,
have had to seal away
my thoughts from kinsmen,
since, long ago,
I sealed my lord
in the darkness of the earth
and from there travelled
winter-minded
over the frozen waves,
sought, hall-lacking,
a treasure-giver,
wherever far or near
I might find someone
in the meadhall
who knew me,
or was willing to console
me, the friendless one,
wow me with wonders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He who has known it understands
how cruel sorrow is as a companion
for the one who has
few beloved friends.
Exile wraps him,
not rings of gold,
a frozen spirit,
not the prosperity of the earth.
He remembers hall-warriors
and ring-givers,
how his gold-giver
treated him to feasting
in his youth.
How all that joy has died!
And so he knows this,
he who must for a long time
forgo the counsel of his
dear lord,
when sorrow and sleep together
wrap him up and bind him.
He dreams in his head
that he hugs and kisses
his lord,
and on his lord&amp;rsquo;s knee
lie his hand and head,
just as he, at times
in days gone by,
enjoyed the gift throne.
Then he wakes back up
a lordless man,
he sees before him
dusky waves,
sea birds bathing,
pruning their feathers,
frost and snow falling,
mixed in with hail.
Then are that much heavier
the wounds of his heart,
grieving after his lord.
His sorrow is renewed
when his mind happens upon
the memory of his kinsmen.
He greets them with joy,
eagerly looks over
the gathering of men -
but they always swim away.
The journey of sailors
never brings back many
known stories.
Grief is renewed
for him who must
always send his
weary heart
over the binding of the waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore I can&amp;rsquo;t think
why my heart does not
darken when I reflect
on all the lives of men
throughout this world,
how they suddenly
left the hall floor,
those proud thanes.
So each day this Middle Earth
crumbles and decays.
Therefore a man cannot become
wise before he has a share
of winters in the world.
A wise man must be patient,
must not be too reckless,
nor too word-hasty
nor too weak a warrior,
nor too rash,
neither too fearful nor cheerful,
nor too greedy of goods,
and never too eager for boasting
before he truly understands.
A man must wait
when he speaks oaths
until the bold one
truly knows
where his heart&amp;rsquo;s intent
will turn.
A wise hero must realize
how ghastly it will be
when all the wealth of this world
lies waste,
as now in various places
around this earth,
walls stand
blown by wind,
covered in snow,
storm-wrecked ruins.
The halls decay,
their leader lies dead,
deprived of joy.
The whole troop
has proudly fallen by the wall.
Some war took them,
carried them on their way.
One, a bird snatched off
over the deep sea.
Another, the gray wolf
tore apart after his death.
Another, buried
dreary-faced
in his grave.
And so He destroyed this place,
the Creator of men,
until missing the noise
of its residents,
the old work of giants
stood idle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He who wisely reflected
on this ruin,
and deeply pondered
this dark life,
wise in experience,
distantly remembered
much slaying,
and spoke these words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where is the horse? Where is the rider?
Where is the treasure-giver?
Where are the hall&amp;rsquo;s joys?
Alas, the bright cups!
Alas, the warrior in mail!
How that time has departed,
dark under night&amp;rsquo;s helm,
as if it never were.
Now stands as a trace of
the dear warband
a wonderously high wall,
snakingly woven.
The warriors habe been snatched away
by the honor of spears,
slaughter-seeking weapons,
that famous fate,
and storms clash against
these stone cliffs,
falling frost
grips the earth,
the clamor of winter.
Then darkness comes;
night&amp;rsquo;s shadow deepens.
From the north approaches
a rough hail storm,
hostile to men.
All is troubled
in this earthly kingdom,
the tide of fate
turns the world under the heavens.
Here is wealth fleeting.
Here are companions fleeting.
Here is man himself fleeting.
Here is kinsman fleeting.
Every foundation of this world
becomes void and vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So spoke the wise one in his mind.
He sat apart in thought.
Good is he who holds onto his faith,
and a warrior must never speak
the grievances of his heart too quickly,
unless he already knows the cure.
A hero must act with conviction.
Good is he who seeks mercy,
the Father&amp;rsquo;s grace in Heaven,
where permanence stands for us all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>After Ragnarok</title>
      <link>http://lambdaviking.com/post/after-ragnarok/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lambdaviking.com/post/after-ragnarok/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Ragnarok is a well known part of the Norse mythological canon presented by Snorri Sturluson. But what happens after the world is destroyed? &lt;em&gt;Gylfaginning&lt;/em&gt; actually tells us, and I&amp;rsquo;ve translated the corresponding section below. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;translation&#34;&gt;Translation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Gangleri says, “Are any gods alive then? Or is there then any earth or heavens?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grey One says, “Up shoots the Earth from the sea and it is then green and fertile. Unsown fields grow there. Vidarr and Vali live such that the sea and Surt’s flame have not hurt them, and they flourish there on Idavollr, where Asgard was before. And then the sons of Thor, Modi and Magni, come there, and they have there Mjollnir. Next, Baldr and Hodr come there from Hell. Everyone then sets themselves together and they talk among themselves and remember their secrets and speak of those times which had been in days gone by. Of the Midgard Serpent and of Fenris Wolf. Then they find themselves in that golden grass that the Aesir had had. So it is said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vidarr and Vali&lt;br /&gt;
flourish as gods&lt;br /&gt;
when Surt’s flame burns.&lt;br /&gt;
Modi and Magni&lt;br /&gt;
shall have Mjollnir&lt;br /&gt;
after Vingnir’s battle-blow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there where is called the forest of Hoddmimir, two hide in Surt’s flame who are called Lif and Leifthrasir, and they have morning dew for food. And from these people comes so great a lineage that the whole world rises again. As is said here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lif and Leifthrasir,&lt;br /&gt;
but they will hide&lt;br /&gt;
in the wood of Hoddmimir.&lt;br /&gt;
Morning dew&lt;br /&gt;
They will have for their food,&lt;br /&gt;
And from there centuries will be nourished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will seem strange to you when the sun has gotten a daughter no less beautiful than she is, and she carries herself on the path of her mother, as it says here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lone daughter carries Alfrodul;&lt;br /&gt;
Fenrir chases the other one.&lt;br /&gt;
So shall it tremble&lt;br /&gt;
when the gods die,&lt;br /&gt;
The mother bears a daughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now if you should ask forth further, then I don’t know from where it could come to you, since I have heard no man speak more about the path of time. Enjoy now what you have gotten.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: The Edda is framed as a prophecy about what is to come for the Aesir, who are, according to Snorri, legendary humans that fled Troy to establish a kingdom in Scandinavia. At this point, we leave the prophecy and go back to the setting where it is first being told.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right then Gangleri heard a great din some way from himself, and went out onto a hill to see. And when he could see more around him, he stands out in the flat field to see no hall and no city. He walked then and travelled his road and came home into his kingdom and said those tidings which he had seen and heard. And after him each man told these stories to the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Aesir set themselves then into legend, ruled their kingdom, and remembered from all these prophecies which were told to them, and gave the same names which before were named to men and the places where they were, until a long time  passed such that men could not remember that they all were the same, those Aesir who now were talked about, and these ones who then were given those same names. There was then the one called Thor, who is also Asathor the Old, who is Okuthor, and by him were known those great works which Thor (Hector) did at Troy. And men think that the Trojans had talked about Ulysses and had called him Loki, because The Trojans were his greatest of unfriends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Saga of Mary</title>
      <link>http://lambdaviking.com/post/saga-of-mary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lambdaviking.com/post/saga-of-mary/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In order to practice my Old Norse, I decided to write up a thorough translation of a short excerpt from the Icelandic Saga of Mary. I&amp;rsquo;ve given the original text underneath, which comes from &lt;em&gt;A New Introduction to Old Norse&lt;/em&gt; edited by Anthony Faulkes. Please let me know if you have any corrections or suggestions! If I post more translations here, I will try to choose longer and more interesting passages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;translation&#34;&gt;Translation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a monastery in that mountain which is called Tumba. There at the monastery stood a church of Michael. In the temple was a likeness of Mary, and it was made such that the Lord sat at her knees, and there was a long silk garment over its head. There came often great thunder and lightning, and a loose bolt hit the church so that it all burned down, but the likeness of Mary was unscathed, as was the pedestal on which it stood. Nowhere was the silk garment that was on the likeness damaged! The monks proclaimed this a miracle, and everyone who heard praised God. We have to pray to God that he free us from evil fire like he did the likeness from this fire-heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;original&#34;&gt;Original&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Munklífi eitt var í fjalli því, er Tumba heitir. Þar stóð Mikjáls kirkja hjá munklífinu. Í musterinu var Maríu líkneskja, ok svá ger sem Dróttinn sæti í knjám henni, ok var silkidúkr breiddr yfir höfuð þeim. Þar kómu opt reiðar stórar ok eldingar, ok laust eitt sinn svá kirkjuna, at hon brand öll, en líkneskja Maríu var heil, ok svá stallrinn, er hon stóð á. Hvergi var á silkidúkinn runnit, er á líkneskjunni var. Munkar lýstu þessi jartegn, ok lofuðu allir Guð, þeir er heyrðu. Vér eigum þess Guð at biðja, at hann leysi oss svá frá eilífum eldi sem líkneskit frá þessum eldshita.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remarks&#34;&gt;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passage describes a miracle in which a statue of Mary struck by lightning does not burn. This event is meant as an allegory for the fate of Christian souls after death: the statue&amp;rsquo;s unburned state represents God&amp;rsquo;s ability to spare mankind from hellfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One odd thing I noticed is that feminine &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;líkneskja&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; in the description of the miracle becomes neuter &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;líkneskit&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; in the final sentence that injects the allegorical interpretation. I can&amp;rsquo;t think of any rhetorical significance that this could have though.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
